Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives
2014-2020
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.MC.004
220 Gigabytes comprised of approximately 24,000 electronic files
The Capstone Archives is an accumulating collection of NYU Abu Dhabi undergraduate senior research projects. The archival colletion includes project files primarily comprised of text-based essays, but may also include filmed performances, interactive media files, and supplemental documents submitted by NYU Abu Dhabi graduating seniors, from 2014 to the present. Submitting their senior Capstone project is a required step for students to complete their undergraduate education at NYUAD and collect their diplomas. Users may access the projects by contacting the Library's Archives and Special Collections staff, who will provide temporary, view-only access to open files.
Biographical / Historical
Conducting Capstone research is a significant part of the undergraduate experience at NYU Abu Dhabi, which every student will engage during their fourth year. Marking the final step before graduating, the year-long research endeavor may result in pursuing an important research question or creative idea, which may take the form of an historical narrative, musical composition, performance, invention, documented experiment, scholarly thesis, or other form appropriate to the student's goals.
To prepare for their Capstone research, all students enroll in a Capstone seminar, led by assigned faculty in each major or program. Some student research, particularly within the Engineering Division, may be conceptualized as a group project, and may build upon research that was conducted by members of an earlier Class. No matter the pursuit, as the program description states, the student is in charge and challenged "to enter unmapped terrain and to extend oneself in making knowledge, reframing conventional approaches to an issue or creating something new."
At the end of each spring semester, each of NYU Abu Dhabi's four academic divisions acknowledge and celebrate Capstone Projects in a variety of ways. These celebrations themselves have become traditions. For example, the Division of Arts and Humanities hosts an annual Capstone Festival; the Engineering Division hosts a special website showcase; and various programs and departments across campus celebrate with senior dinners, acknowledgement, and congratulations events. An annual Capstone Projects anthology is also produced and widely shared. As a condition of graduation (as of 2018), students must submit their project to the Library, where the collections is managed as part of the University Archives.
Scope and Contents
One of the most frequently used collections of the University Archives, the Capstone Archives is the University's accumulating collection of submitted senior research projects, beginning with the Class of 2014 and continuing to the present. The collection is a living, growing digital collection that is being preserved collaboratively by Archives and Special Collections and the Center for Digital Scholarship, in the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Organized into series by academic division, and major within, the project files consist primarily of text-based essays. Some projects also include other products and deliverables such as copies of films, as well as filmed performances; interactive media files (such as programmed Virtual Reality and video game software files); and supplemental documents such as photographs of installations and prototypes. As the projects represent all majors across disciplines, a broad range of topics and research areas are explored across the collection.
In some cases, particularly in the Engineering Division, Capstone projects are group projects, or may continue research that was begun by a previous group under direction of the same faculty member.
Upon submission, students write and provide their own summary abstracts of the project, which are included in the container list of each open project described.
Student creators are given the option to restrict their project for a period of time, and some do choose to do so. There are a variety of reasons why this might happen. For example, some students may wish to continue their research beyond their time at NYU Abu Dhabi, and are not yet ready to make it public. This finding aid represents only unrestricted and open projects. Administration of restricted files is managed by Archives and Special Collections.
In addition to project files, which make up the core of the collection, a series of "Other Capstone Documentation" includes records such as video recordings of students describing their projects; photographs of installations and prototypes taken by campus photographers (as opposed to those submitted by students); and ephemera from Capstone Festivals and events. Although intellectually part of the Capstone Archives, digital content in this series is stored and managed separately, maintained as digital assets by the Center for Digital Scholarship and unprocessed, but available for reviewing upon request and with guidance from the archivist.
This collection is open to the public, and by far its most frequent user group includes NYUAD juniors and seniors who seek out the collection as they embark on their own research. Student researchers browse and read past Capstone projects, for example, for inspiration; to gauge if an idea has been explored before; to carry on previous research; or, as part of a literature review to integrate into the project essay.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into several series, beginning with the four academic divisions. Within those series, files are arranged into sub-series by major. Within each major, projects are then listed chronologically by submission year, and alphabetically by last name of student within.
For group projects with multiple authors, the project is arranged alphabetically by last name, although all names of participants are present in the title.
As each project is considered a unique project, all files will have a component unique identifier, which is the Capstone Project number or "CP#."
A fifth series, "Other Capstone Documentation," is unprocessed as of the publication of this finding aid, but arrangement of files internally correspond to Division and CP#.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Capstone Projects and their accompanying supplemental documents are uploaded to an administrative server directly by students, which is managed by NYUAD IT. Instructions and a form are accessible via the NYU Abu Dhabi intranet. Submitted projects are then transferred to Library repositories by the archivists for integration and preservation as part of the University Archives.
Other Capstone documentation is acquired through various means directy from individual programs, and stewarded by the Library's digital content specialists in the Center for Digital Scholarship.
Conditions Governing Access
Archived Capstone Projects that are open and unrestricted are available for viewing onsite in the Archives and Special Collections reading room, or temporary view-only remote access may be arranged. Each Capstone Project has a unique identifier defined by year of submission and a four-digit number (ex: 2019-0001). When requesting access, this number is needed for retrieval of files.
University and Colleges -- Research; College students--research
- Arts & Humanities Division Projects, 2014-2019
  - Arab Crossroads Studies
    - Tessen, Alice. Compounding British Interests in Zanzibar: Accounting for Continuities between Sultanate and Protectorate., 2014; 2014-0003 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0003)
      Scope and Contents
      Abstract: In the first decades of colonial rule, British imperial administrators abolished slavery in Zanzibar, but their attempts to persuade Arab landowners to embrace wage labor in the place of slave labor fell on deaf ears. The once-powerful Arab clove planters had lost much of their political influence over the course of the 19th century, and many were heavily in debt to Indian moneylenders. The development of this situation is vital to understanding how colonial policies were implemented and how Zanzibaris navigated the changes which occurred in the early colonial period. This thesis analyzes the current state of scholarship on Zanzibar's early colonial history, and argues that there has been a tendency for studies to rely too heavily on casting 1890 as a turning point, which has the effect of downplaying continuities between pre-colonial and early colonial processes of economic, political, and social change. I advocate for a rethinking of temporal boundaries in future research on this subject, and I examine two processes, the slave trade and the British exploitation of Indian merchants, which demonstrate the theoretical benefits that can be derived from crossing the imagined border between the pre-colonial and colonial eras.
      Colonialism History Middle East; Oman; Zanzibar; British Empire; Agriculture/Farms; Enslavement; Debt
    - Hennig, Clare Elizabeth. The 'Red Line' Of Journalism: Shifting Visions Of The Media In The UAE., 2016; 2016-0004; This project focuses on the gap between the vision of journalism in the UAE and the position of the press in practice. The first two chapters piece together a history of journalism in the country alongside a theoretical discussion of the role and responsibilities of the press in society. This is followed by an examination of the UAE's canon of media law and a news analysis of national newspapers. Despite a push to foster journalism in the country, the legal framework has not yet caught up with the purported vision of the press. This dichotomy of informal promises on the one hand and the formal legal cannon on the other is one of the biggest challenges the press currently faces in the UAE. This creates uncertainty in the newsroom, ultimately leading to an inclination towards self-censorship when reporting sensitive issues because of a fear of crossing the 'red line' of journalism. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0004)
      Abstract: This project focuses on the gap between the vision of journalism in the UAE and the position of the press in practice. The first two chapters piece together a history of journalism in the country alongside a theoretical discussion of the role and responsibilities of the press in society. This is followed by an examination of the UAE's canon of media law and a news analysis of national newspapers. Despite a push to foster journalism in the country, the legal framework has not yet caught up with the purported vision of the press. This dichotomy of informal promises on the one hand and the formal legal cannon on the other is one of the biggest challenges the press currently faces in the UAE. This creates uncertainty in the newsroom, ultimately leading to an inclination towards self-censorship when reporting sensitive issues because of a fear of crossing the 'red line' of journalism.
    - Leathley, Emma. War of Words: How UAE Think Tanks Use War On Terrorism Discourse To Produce Knowledge And Promote Policy., 2016; 2016-0005; This project uses discourse analysis of the terrorism literature of four UAE think tanks--Al Mesbar Center for Studies and Research, the Emirates Center for Strategic Studies and Research, TRENDS Research & Advisory, and Hedayah--to examine how think tanks in the UAE use the discourse of the war on terrorism in their policy research. It found that UAE think tanks mimic and adapt various forms and stages of the American discourse on the war on terrorism. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0005)
      Abstract: This project uses discourse analysis of the terrorism literature of four UAE think tanks--Al Mesbar Center for Studies and Research, the Emirates Center for Strategic Studies and Research, TRENDS Research & Advisory, and Hedayah--to examine how think tanks in the UAE use the discourse of the war on terrorism in their policy research. It found that UAE think tanks mimic and adapt various forms and stages of the American discourse on the war on terrorism.
    - Plottel, Louis. "The Lighter Our Task, The Heavier Our Burden" An Ethnography Of Political Dissidence Among Punks And Anarchists In Indonesia., 2016; 2016-0010; Punk and anarchism, as lived practices that espouse anti-authoritarianism and prefigurative politics as their guiding principles, share a close affinity. Yet, the political value of punk has tended to be overlooked in favor of the punk "identity." This paper considers the overlapping politics of anarchists and punks in Yogyakarta, Indonesia, through ethnographic description of the everyday practice of political dissidence. I approach punk from an anarchist point of view, analysing it as an expression of prefigurative politics. Drawing upon fieldwork with members of a newly formed anarchist website, anarkis.org, and a punk squat in the north of the city, I show how political dissidents in Indonesia are fostering connections to global punk and anarchist movements through their everyday lives. I contend that punks play an important role in the embodiment of anarchism as a political way of being, while revealing the contours and complexities of radical political movements in Indonesia. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0010)
      Abstract: Punk and anarchism, as lived practices that espouse anti-authoritarianism and prefigurative politics as their guiding principles, share a close affinity. Yet, the political value of punk has tended to be overlooked in favor of the punk "identity." This paper considers the overlapping politics of anarchists and punks in Yogyakarta, Indonesia, through ethnographic description of the everyday practice of political dissidence. I approach punk from an anarchist point of view, analysing it as an expression of prefigurative politics. Drawing upon fieldwork with members of a newly formed anarchist website, anarkis.org, and a punk squat in the north of the city, I show how political dissidents in Indonesia are fostering connections to global punk and anarchist movements through their everyday lives. I contend that punks play an important role in the embodiment of anarchism as a political way of being, while revealing the contours and complexities of radical political movements in Indonesia.
    - Levinson, Melissa. Constructing an Enemy: Representations of the Middle East and Islam in U.S. Textbooks, 2018; 2018-0007; My project investigates the dominant portrayals of Arabs and Muslims in history textbooks in the United States. Specifically, my study concludes that world history textbooks perpetuate the notion of a "rise and fall" of the Middle East and Islamic faith and present Arabs and Muslims as antithetical to American values. My research further seeks to determine why these representations came about. In other words, what political, economic, and social forces have influenced the negative portrayals we see in American textbooks? I have found that these representations are in part due to a rise of conservative voices in educational curricular development since the 1980s that has created an education system that narrowly defines the American nation by its white, Christian roots and seeks to preserve the notion of American exceptionalism. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0007)
      Abstract: My project investigates the dominant portrayals of Arabs and Muslims in history textbooks in the United States. Specifically, my study concludes that world history textbooks perpetuate the notion of a "rise and fall" of the Middle East and Islamic faith and present Arabs and Muslims as antithetical to American values. My research further seeks to determine why these representations came about. In other words, what political, economic, and social forces have influenced the negative portrayals we see in American textbooks? I have found that these representations are in part due to a rise of conservative voices in educational curricular development since the 1980s that has created an education system that narrowly defines the American nation by its white, Christian roots and seeks to preserve the notion of American exceptionalism.
    - Burlin, Carl Alexander. "A New Paradigm" for Syrian Refugees?: Development, Displacement Management and (Dis-)Empowerment in Jordan, 2019; 2019-0002 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0002)
      This paper examines the extent to which development planning can provide solutions to protracted displacement crises by looking at the case of the "Jordan Compact," a multi-stakeholder policy agreement that promised to turn the Syrian "refugee crisis" in Jordan into a "development opportunity." Drawing on fieldwork conducted in Jordan over the summer of 2018 I argue that the Jordan Compact failed to reach target outcomes due to a number of structural implementation challenges, including policy decontextualization and a competitive development architecture. In terms of the empowerment of Syrian refugees, however, the failure of the Jordan Compact was not so much a question of flawed implementation as it was of the "anti-politics" of development-based refugee policy. Syrians in Jordan do not just suffer from "underdevelopment," but also from a weak protection regime that circumvents the question of durable solutions and facilitates exploitation, discrimination, and abuse. In this way, a critique of the Jordan Compact should first and foremost highlight the political failure of the compact to strengthen refugee protection and offer a durable, long-term solution to the refugee crisis.
    - Mikhalkovich, Alena. Perceptions and Practices of Emirati visitors at Louvre Abu Dhabi, 2019; 2019-0027 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0027)
      This research studies Louvre Abu Dhabi and the "Roads of Arabia" exhibition, its role in nation-building and UAE branding, and its reception by the local population. Firstly, I examine the museum's reconciliation of local and universal heritage, the UAE nation-building and branding. Secondly, I study Emiratis' reception of such big Western-style museum projects. I argue that Louvre Abu Dhabi brand becomes regionalized and appropriated for UAE nation-branding and regional diplomacy. At the same time, I demonstrate that Emiratis, despite appreciation of the universal narrative, view the museum primarily as a branding project and a tourist-oriented establishment, disapproving its emphasis on the Western culture and insufficient reach out to the local population. Hence, Emiratis desire bigger representation of the local heritage at Louvre, seeing it as worthy of being part of the universal narrative. In addition, I argue that Louvre Abu Dhabi apart from mitigating the nation-building and branding contradictions, gives a way for a young educated upper- and middle-class Emiratis to practice and express their elitist cultural identity in contradistinction to the older, less educated, and religiously conservative Emiratis.
    - Plaschke, Jakob. LGBT+-Activism in Tunisia: Brokering Progressive Politics Independently, 2020; 2020-0001 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0001)
      Based on two fieldwork trips and extensive interviewing, this capstone looks broadly at how LGBT+-activist organizations function in the political context that is contemporary Tunisia. The capstone consists of four main chapters, each contributing separately to the existing literature on the topic, but also coming together as a whole. The first chapter is a historical account of LGBT+-activism in Tunisia, identifying important periods and ruptures. The second chapter is a contemporary mapping of the Tunisian LGBT+-activist community, focused on organizations' differences, interplay and conflicts. The third chapter argues that Tunisian LGBT+-activists are doing a good job at navigating complex political structures to their benefit and also details the concrete work being carried out. The final chapter argues that if Tunisian LGBT+-activists continue to self-evaluate and improve their ability to assert influence, they have a unique chance to become brokers of broad political alliances over progressive social policies. This is in part due to the fact that LGBT+-rights are not a politically polarizing issue and in part because the organizations are not tainted by affiliations with the Ben Ali dictatorship.
      Queer, activism, LGBT, Tunisia, North Africa, MENA, politics, history, Tunis
    - Young Kim, Ji. Never كافي: Understanding Emirati Youth Subculture development in Abu Dhabi Specialty Cafes, 2020; 2020-0002 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0002)
      With the increased number of specialty cafes in Abu Dhabi, Emirati youth have appropriated cafes as a space of sociability. Through field interviews and ethnographic research, this paper investigates how the influx of specialty cafes has developed the practice of sociability between young Emiratis, and how these spaces of sociability affect their modes of identification. I argue that Abu Dhabi youth transform specialty cafes into a young people's place that is socially acceptable while encouraging them to expand their social circle beyond their family. By doing so, they not only create a subculture inside this social space but also reconstruct social norms to fit the category of the youth. I discuss the themes of anonymity, privacy, gender hierarchy and the performance of identity. Just like the title indicates, there is "never enough" layers and information on how cafes can be understood Abu Dhabi.
      Abu Dhabi, Youth Culture, Specialty Cafe, Anonymity, Subculture, Gender
    - Ammagui, Nada. Aesthetic Assertion: Taste-Making at the Sharjah Biennial, 2020; 2020-0003 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0003)
      Art has long served as a platform for cultural exploration, representation, and exchange, particularly in the space of international art fairs and biennials (Althuser 2008; Kirshenblatt-Gimblatt 2007). From souqs and Kalba Nature Reserve to canopied saris and dancing chess pieces, the Sharjah Biennial, the first art biennial in the Arabian Penninsula, takes visitors on a physical trip through Sharjah and an ideological journey through global contemporary artistic forms and themes. How does the Sharjah Biennial's juxtaposition of local traditions and internationally relevant concerns shape local aesthetic tastes? How do spatial and aesthetic discourses affect these tastes? This capstone paper investigates the effect of these discourses, grounded in local historical narratives, on the creation of aesthetic preferences. With this research, I challenge hegemonic rhetoric on modernization and identity retro-formation in Gulf art scenes by arguing that the Sharjah Biennial draws on local histories to shape its future. I fill a gap in contemporary art and biennial literature by offering the first academic paper on the Sharjah Biennial and by shedding light on the roles of art events in the shaping of local aesthetics, contributing to a wider understanding of contemporary Gulf cultures.
      Sharjah, UAE, contemporary art, biennials, aesthetics, anthropology, habitus, milieu, exhibition
    - Garcia, Sussan. Kafala and Binding are Synonyms: A Consequence of Capitalist Class Formation in Ethnic Regimes in the United Arab Emirates and Israel, 2020; 2020-0004 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0004)